Guide to the Pacific University President Thomas McClelland Records 1892-1914
Pacific University Archives
Pacific University President Thomas McClelland Records
1892-1914
RG.3.104
Pacific University, Archives http://www.pacificu.edu/library/services/archives/ 2043 College Way Forest Grove, OR, 97116 503-352-1405 archives@pacificu.edu
0.5 cubic feet 1 box
Thomas McClelland was Pacific University's fourth president, serving from 1892-1900. This collection is primarily composed of correspondence that President McClelland received and wrote during his time at Pacific University.
McClelland, Thomas
No accruals are expected.
This collection is primarily composed of incoming correspondence that President McClelland received during his time at Pacific University. The most common topic within the letters is fundraising, followed by requests for course catalogs and inquiries about affairs at Pacific University. Enclosed in one letter, there is a set of reports by an undercover police agent who observed illegal liquor sales at a drug store in Forest Grove. There are also several manuscripts of writings by McClelland related to Pacific University, commencement programs, and other materials.
Collection is open for research.
Biographical Note
Thomas McClelland was Pacific University's fourth president, serving from 1892-1900. Born in 1849 in County Derry, Ireland, he immigrated to the United States with his family at the age of three. He earned an A.B. at Oberlin College in Ohio in 1875, and then attended Union Theological Seminary in New York and Andover Theological Seminary in Massachussetts. He then taught philosophy for 11 years at Tabor College in Iowa.
When McClelland became Pacific University's president in 1892, he stepped into a tense political atmosphere. The previous president, Jacob Ellis, had resigned over the issue of sectarian control of the university. Ellis, along with one half of the Board of Trustees, favored bringing Pacific under the formal control of the Congregationalist denomination. The other half of the Board of Trustees wanted Pacific to remain non-denominational. McClelland's task was to heal the fractures between the two parties. He fashioned a compromise, amending the charter to give a two-thirds majority of the Board to the Congregationalists, without putting the school under the denomination's direct control. This solution allowed Pacific to retain a special relationship with the Congregationalist Church, while staying a non-sectarian school.
Student life at Pacific evolved considerably during McClelland's presidency. The football team played its first game in 1893. Men's baseball, basketball and track also began early in the decade; women's basketball and track began in 1899. Extracurricular clubs centered on debate, music, drama, archery and the YMCA/YWCA flourished. The Index, the student newspaper, was established in 1893r; The Heart of Oak, the student yearbook, was first issued a year later. McClelland raised funds to construct Marsh Memorial Hall, which became the center of campus administration. He also helped to recruit two influential faculty members, Henry Liberty Bates and Mary Frances Farnham, and oversaw Pacific's 50th anniversary celebrations. Student enrollment in the university doubled during his term.
The constant need to raise money for the university took its toll on McClelland however. He often travelled for months at a time to locations across the United States, looking for sources of funding. When he resigned in 1900, he explained, "I had begun to feel the strain of the constant canvass for money at such a great distance from home and I was keenly sensible to the dact that under the circumstances I could not do for the institution all that, in my judgment, a president should do for a college," (Letter to Myron Eells, 10 Jan 1901). On leaving Pacific, he took a new position as the president of Knox College in Illinois, where he remained for 17 years. He continued to advocate for Pacific University even after leaving. As a member of the board of directors of the Carnegie Foundation, he very likely had a hand in securing its funds for a new dormitory and a library at Pacific University, which were built in 1907 and 1912.
Most of the biographical information above has been adapted from Splendid Audacity: The Story of Pacific University (Gary Miranda and Rick Read, 2000).
Pacific University
Universities and colleges--Oregon
Colleges and universities
Correspondence
Education administrators, postsecondary
- Correspondence
  All correspondence is addressed to Thomas McClelland unless otherwise noted.
  - Adams, F.H. (Banker at The Citizens Bank, Vancouver, Washington), 1906 (Folder 1)
    Regarding rumors of financial irregularities related to President Ferrin and the building of Herrick Hall.
  - Bates, Henry L. (Professor at Pacific University), 1913-1914 (Folder 1)
    Two letters written after McClelland had left Pacific University; regarding personal matters and the state of school.
  - Billings, Julie, 1899 (Folder 1)
    2 letters regarding donations.
  - Burrell, Rom?, 1899 (Folder 1)
    Regarding a donation.
  - Collins, J.H., 1891 (Folder 1)
    Requesting a Pacific University catalog.
  - Converse, John H., 1895-1898 (Folder 1)
    Three letters regarding donations.
  - Cook, F.R., 1895 (Folder 1)
    Enclosing a check.
  - Corbell, H. W., 1897 (Folder 1)
  - Davis, Napoleon (Trustee of Pacific University), 1902- (Folder 2)
    Four incoming and four outgoing Regarding Pacific University business after McClelland had left for his next position. Includes discussion of the appointment of a new president and the Pearsons' fund.
  - Davis, Oscar F. (Folder 2)
  - Eells, Myron (Trustee of Pacific University) to Mrs. McClelland (Folder 2)
    One outgoing letter to Eells explaining his reasons for resigning from Pacific University; and one incoming letter asking for a photograph of Thomas McClelland, to be published in a history of Pacific University. This letter was found accompanied by a humorous photograph of a man dumping another man into a pond.
  - Ferguson, William Dwight (Professor at Pacific University), 1909 (Folder 2)
    Two letters regarding fundraising for Pacific University.
  - Lloyd, Francis E. (Professor at Columbia University), 1903 (Folder 2)
    Copy of a letter from McClelland to Lloyd regarding a donation to Pacific University.
  - Ferrera, A., 1891 (Folder 2)
    Regarding sending a son to Tualatin Academy.
  - Ferrin, William N. (Professor and later President of Pacific University), 1897 (Folder 2)
    Regarding Pacific University business. For later letters between McClelland and Ferrin, see: Pacific University President William N. Ferrin Records (RG.3.105).
  - Fitch, Frank S. (Pastor of the First Congregational Church, Buffalo, New York), 1897 (Folder 2)
    Recommendation letter.
  - French, H.A., 1892 (Folder 2)
  - Hinman, Alanson (Trustee of Pacific University), 1900 (Folder 2)
  - Holmes, Samuel Van Vranken (Pastor? of Westminster Church, Buffalo, New York), 1897 (Folder 2)
  - Hoskin?, John, 1892 (Folder 2)
  - Johnson, Myrtle, 1892? (Folder 2)
    Requesting a Pacific University catalog for 5 Oregon women: Echo Koonly, Ilda Poppleton, Anna Luster, Olivia Jacobs, and Laura Richards.
  - Kellogg (Folder 2)
    Fragment of a letter from McClelland to Kellogg.
  - Liquor Investigation Reports, 1899 (Folder 3)
    Contains reports from an "agent" regarding the sales of beer and liquor in Forest Grove. The reports, which appear to describe clandestine sales in a Forest Grove drug store contrary to state law, are enclosed in correspondence from McClelland's attorney and a "superintendent," who was probably from the Portland police.
  - Macrum, J.A., 1900 (Folder 3)
    Two outgoing letters and one incoming letter regarding the Dr. Pearsons endowment for Pacific University.
  - Maile, John L., 1902 (Folder 3)
    Outgoing letter recommending "President Warren" as the new president of Pacific University.
  - Marsh, Joseph Walker (Professor and Librarian at Pacific University), 1891-1906 (Folder 4)
    Regarding Pacific University business, including McClelland's acceptance of the presidency, the school's finances, recruitment of faculty, and dealings with the Carnegie Foundation. Includes many outgoing letters from McClelland to Marsh, and 1 incoming letter from Marsh to McClelland.
  - McAdams, L.U. (Superintendant of Oregon City Public Schools), 1899 (Folder 4)
    Recommending two prospective students for admission.
  - Pearson, Alice L., 1901 (Folder 5)
  - Pearson, A.H., 1900-1901 (Folder 5)
    Three outgoing letters from McClelland to Pearson regarding recommendations for the next president of Pacific University.
  - Pearsons, D.K., 1897-1898 (Folder 5)
    Regarding donations.
  - Reins?, H.A., 1892 (Folder 5)
  - Robertson, James R., 1891 (Folder 5)
  - Robertson, Thomas D., 1895-1898 (Folder 5)
  - Roland, Alice, 1892 (Folder 5)
  - Rutledge, J.B.C., 1892 (Folder 5)
  - Savage, G.S.F. (Secretary of the Chicago Theological Society), 1898 (Folder 5)
    1 incoming and 1 outgoing letter regarding approaching Dr. Pearson about donations.
  - Schindler, G. (Folder 5)
    Letter of recommendation.
  - Shiack, W.S., 1893 (Folder 6)
    Requesting a recommendation.
  - Staver, Daniel (Field Agent for Pacific University) (Folder 6)
    Requesting Pacific University catalog for a list of students in Scappoose, Oregon.
  - Strong, James W. (Carleton College President), 1898 (Folder 6)
  - Tibbals, William H., 1898 (Folder 6)
  - Warren, Anna S., 1906 (Folder 6)
    One incoming and one outgoing letter regarding the burning of Pacific University's Herrick Hall (the women's dormitory) and fundraising for reconstruction.
  - Warren, Frank M. (Treasurer of Pacific University), 1905 (Folder 6)
    Several incoming and outgoing letters regarding the funding of a library for Pacific University through the Carnegie Foundation, and various other financial matters.
  - Warren, H.K., 1900 (Folder 6)
    Congratulations on his new position.
  - Whittelsey, Theodore (Professor of Chemistry), 1896 (Folder 6)
    Lengthy letter regarding Pacific University's chemistry program, discussing course credits and laboratory work, and comparing it to that of Amherst College and Beloit College.
  - Winchester, B.S. (Folder 6)
    Outgoing letter from McClelland to Winchester regarding personal matters.
  - Empty envelopes, ca. 1890s (Folder 6)
  - Fragile correspondence (Folder 7)
    Fragile original copies of letters on onionskin paper. Photocopies of the items in this folder have been photocopied and filed in the main series of correspondence.
- Writings
  - "Ground was broken with appropriate ceremonies on Commencement Day ..." Manuscript draft of an essay in support of fundraising to build Marsh Hall., 1893 (Folder 8)
  - Notes about correspondence, 1892? (Folder 8)
  - "Pacific University, its origins and history." Manuscript draft., circa 1895 (Folder 8)
  - "Under the Oaks." Song about Pacific University. Manuscript., 1890s? (Folder 8)
  - "Romans 10:14-15." Sermon notes. (Folder 8)
- Miscellaneous
  - Financial documents, 1882-1892 (Folder 9)
    Includes a life insurance policy, bank shares, a mortgage bond, and a receipt.
  - Printed ephemera, 1892-1913 (Folder 10)
    Includes McClelland's inauguration program (1892), commencement programs (1893 and 1897), a circular letter and pamphlet regarding fundraising for Pacific University (1899?), and a calendar of the First Congregational Church in Forest Grove (1913).
  - Photograph of a man dumping another man into a pond, 1890s (Folder 11)